あぁ… そうですね…｡
(銀時)あ～ だりぃ～！
設定とか言うなよ…｡
(神楽)暑くて 脳ﾐｿ溶けそうｱﾙ｡
(新八)あぁ… そういえば➡
こんな ｶﾝｶﾝ照りのなか
歩けるかよ！
こう暑いと
何もやる気おきませんよね｡
どっかに来いとか
言われてませんでしたっけ？
(神楽)私 夜兎だから
日ざしに弱いっていう設定ｱﾙ｡
もう いいだろう？
今日のｱﾆﾒもなしで…｡
次回を お楽しみに～！
あぁ… だりぃ！
(神楽)｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣でよくある…
作者取材のため 休載ね｡
じゃ… 今日の 『銀魂』は
休止ということで…｡
Man...so lazy...
It's so hot, it feels like my brain's gonna melt...
Oh yeah, now that I think about it, weren't we supposed to be somewhere right now?
Right, like we can walk in this blazing heat!
My character is from the Yato clan so I have a weakness to sunlight. Well, that's what they say.
Stop talking about the writer's back-story.
You're right. I don't feel like doing anything when it's hot like this.
So what do you say?
Cancel today's show, too?
It often happens in JUMP. They take a break because the author is out collecting material for the story.
Okay, in that case, GinTama will be taking a break today.
Please look forward to our next show!
Man...so lazy...
[Actually, it's not a day off. So let's get this done. Get to work!]
[Remember, Ochi-san from the neighborhood association, told you to come to the temple.]
(賑わう声)
Yakitori
Yakisoba
Takoyaki
(祭り囃子の音)
Goldfish scooping
Oh, the sound of festival music...
あぁ… 祭り囃子の音が…｡
(神楽)いいなぁ…
みんな お祭り行けて…｡
How nice. Everyone but me gets to enjoy the festival.
私も ﾎﾞｿﾎﾞｿの焼きそば
食べたいｱﾙ！
I want to eat dried-up fried noodles too.
ｸﾞﾀﾞｸﾞﾀﾞ言ってんじゃないよ！
しかたねえだろう！
Stop whining.
We've got no choice.
こいつは毎年
かぶき町で行われている➡
This event takes place every year in Kabukicho.
恒例の行事なんだから…｡
毎年交代で 町内の誰かが➡
We all have to take turns doing this job each year.
こういう役回りを
やらなきゃならねえの！
いわば かぶき町で
生きていくための掟だよ！
It's kind of like our civic duty as residents of Kabukicho.
それに こいつを毎年
取り仕切ってる役員の➡
But let's not forget Ochi, the ol' man who runs it every year...
落ってｵｯｻﾝが うるさくてよぉ！
…ん!?
...is a real pain in the butt.
Sakata-san, I told you multiple times to be here at noon for the rehearsal.
(落)坂田さん！
打ち合わせするから➡
昼には来てって あれほど
言ってあったはずだよね？
ﾊｧ…｡
打ち合わせなしに大会始めて➡
What are you going to do if there's an accident or someone gets injured because we didn't rehearse first?!
[The Kabukicho Haunted House]
ｹｶﾞ人や事故がでたら
どうするつもりなんだ ああっ!?
Forget it!
(落)もういい！
やる気のないﾔﾂは帰れっ！
If you don't feel like doing it, then go home.
今年は ﾎﾞｸ一人でやる！
I'll do it all by myself this year!
Sorry about that.
すみませんでした｡
じゃあ…｡
See ya.
よ～し！
その一言が聞きたかったぁ！
Good! That's all I wanted to hear from you.
もう 怒ってないから
戻っておいで～！
I forgive you, so get back here.
Huh?
あれ？ …ちょっと 坂田さん!?
Hey? Sakata-san?!
(落)あのあれ… ｽｲｶとか
いっぱいあるよ！ 坂田さ～ん！
Um... I've got lots of watermelon and other stuff for you!! Sakata-san!!
I'm sorry, Sakata-san! I was out of line. Sakata-san!!
すみませんでしたっ 坂田さん！
調子にのってました！
坂田さ～ん!!
["Like a Haunted House, Life is Filled with Horrors"]
まったく… 頼むよ ﾎﾝﾄに!!
Come on, gimme a break.
こんな時間じゃ
もう ﾘﾊやる時間もないよ！
At this hour, we don't even have time to do a rehearsal.
Well, I'm really sorry.
いや… ﾎﾝﾄ すみませんでした！
You keep saying you're sorry, but you don't sound apologetic at all.
(落)いや… すみませんでしたって
ｷﾐたち➡
さっきから
すみませんの態度じゃないよね!?
(神楽)すみませんっしたぁ！
Sorry!
私も長年 生きてきたけどね…
こんな攻撃的な➡
You know, I've been around a long time,
and that's the most offensive apology I've ever heard.
｢すみませんでした｣は
初めてだよ…｡
どうするんだぁ!?
What are we going to do?
What if we start the haunted house without a rehearsal and someone gets hurt?
このまま ぶっつけ本番で
肝試しを始めて➡
もし ｹｶﾞ人でもでたら…｡
It's my job to make sure this event runs smoothly and safely every year.
(落)私の役目はね…
毎年 この行事を➡
無事 何ごともなく
とり行うことなんだぁ！
楽しい肝試し大会で 事故なんて➡
We can't let anyone get hurt during this festival's haunted house.
絶対あってはならない
ことだからね！
頭に矢が刺さってるﾔﾂに
言われても しっくりこないｱﾙ｡
It's hard to take someone with an arrow sticking out of his head seriously.
これは 事故じゃない…
戦だから！
It's for the role I'm playing.
It's from a battle.
戦で負けて… っていう
設定だから！
I'm a battle casualty. That's the setting.
戦でｹｶﾞは ありｱﾙか？
So battle injuries are acceptable?
戦でｹｶﾞは ありだよ｡
Yes, battle injuries are acceptable.
But if you think about it, battles were instigated by the rulers of the time for their own purposes...
でも… 戦も 時の権力者たちが➡
ﾃﾒｴの都合で 勝手に
おっぱじめたｹﾝｶであって➡
巻き込まれる
ｵﾚたち庶民からすれば➡
so for commoners like us, a battle would feel a lot like an accident.
戦も事故と大差ないと
ｵﾚは思うね｡
んだよぉ もう！
Oh my god! What is wrong with you people!
You want me to take this arrow out?
この矢を取ればいいのか!?
この矢が気にくわないのかぁ!?
Don't you like my arrows?
とにかくね！ 肝試しに来るような
お客さんってのは➡
Anyway, customers who come to the haunted house are adrenaline junkies.
もう はしゃいじゃって
はしゃいじゃって…➡
They're high on the adrenaline rush, so who knows what they'll do?
ﾎﾞﾙﾃｰｼﾞ ｸﾞｰﾝ上がっちゃってるから
何するか わかんないのぉ！
だから 気をつけないと ﾎﾝﾄ…
思わぬ事故とか起こるからね！
That's why we have to be ready for any unexpected accident that might occur.
心配いらないっすよ！
Don't worry about it. Our adrenaline is always running low.
ｵﾚたちは
ﾎﾞﾙﾃｰｼﾞ 下がりっぱなしだから｡
Before you know it, we'll have drained all their excess energy.
子供たちの はしゃいでた気持も
いつしか沈んでいきますよ！
そんな肝試し ｲﾔだからっ！
盛り上がんないからっ!!
I don't want a lethargic haunted house!
It has to be spine-tingling!
大丈夫ですってぇ…
ﾘﾊなんかしなくても➡
No problem. We don't need a rehearsal.
ﾜｰｷｬｰ言ってりゃ お客さんも
つられて ﾜｰｷｬｰ言いますよ！
All we have to do is say, "wah" and "kyah" and the scared customers will say "wah" and "kyah" with us.
(新八)
まっ ﾎﾞｸらに任せといてください！
Just leave it to us.
(３人)よし！ じゃあ いくか！
All right, let's do this!
(落)おいぃぃぃっ!!
ﾜｰｷｬｰって何!?
Hey! We want "wah" and "kyah" to be shrieks of fear, not death cries!
悲鳴じゃなくて
断末魔の叫びぃっ!?
What do you guys think you're here for?
何しに来たの？ ｷﾐたち！
それ 肝試しじゃないよね？
肝取りにいってるよね!?
We're trying to test people's courage.
Not rip their hearts out!
それぐらいやんねえと
今のｽﾚたｶﾞｷは ﾋﾞﾋﾞんないっすよ！
You gotta be this extreme to get a reaction out of all the jaded kids these days.
ﾀﾞﾒだって！ 人の話聞いてる!?
No! Didn't you hear what I said?
I said I don't want any accidents or injuries!
ｹｶﾞとか事故とか
だしたくないんだって!!
…で 何 その格好？
So what's with that getup?
ｵﾊﾞｹの衣装 持ってこいって
言ったよね!?
Didn't I ask you to bring ghost costumes?
お前ら 全員…
ただの殺人鬼じゃねえか!!
Not dress like bloodthirsty killers!!
本当に怖いもの…｡
You know what's really scary...?
それはね… 人間の心です！
Let me tell you...
It's the human heart.
Do I look like I'm interested in your muddled insights?
ｵﾒｴの価値観なんて
知りたくもねえよっ！
私はちゃんと ｵﾊﾞｹｱﾙよ！
I'm a ghost, just like you asked.
ｶｸﾞﾘｰﾅは 殺人鬼の魂が➡
My character, Kaguriina is a doll that is possessed by the ghost of a serial killer.
人形にのり移ったって
設定なんだよ！
知らねえよっ そんな設定！
I've never even heard of such a character!
All I see is a hillbilly sushi chef.
包丁持った家なき子にしか
見えねえよっ!!
ﾌﾌﾌﾌﾌｯ…｡
お前にいたっては➡
As for you, god knows what the hell you're supposed to be.
もう 何がやりてえのか
わかんねえよっ！
あん？ あれっすよ！
ﾔｸｻﾞのｵﾊﾞｹっすよ！
Huh? You know, the ghost of a yakuza.
ﾊﾞｶの考え方だよ！
怖いものと怖いものを足したら➡
What an idiotic idea!
Combining two scary things doesn't equal greater scariness!
ものすごく怖いものになると
思ってる➡
ﾊﾞｶの考え方だよぉぉっ!!
Only a total idiot would think of that!
Go change your costumes! Change them!!
衣装ﾁｪﾝｼﾞだ！ 衣装ﾁｪﾝｼﾞ!!
去年使ったやつ
まだ残ってるから！
We still have the ones left over from last year, so put those on for now.
とりあえず 着替えてっ!!
Sorry about that, Ochi-san.
落さん すみませんっ！
じゃあ これﾔｸｻﾞってのはﾅｼで➡
Okay, forget the yakuza ghost. I'll be the ghost of a security guard.
ｶﾞｰﾄﾞﾏﾝのｵﾊﾞｹにします！
…それなら いいでしょ？
That'll work, right?
(落)いいわけねえだろっ!!
なにそれ!?
Like hell it would!
What? Why are you looking at me like you solved the problem?!
なに 問題解決したぁ…
みたいな顔してんの!?
ん～ まぁ 前よりは
ましになったよ｡
Well, at least it's better than before.
寺に吸血鬼ってどうよ？
どういうｾﾝｽ！
So there's a vampire at the temple now?
Yeah, where's the logic in that?
みんな ﾊﾞﾗﾊﾞﾗ ｱﾙ！
世界観 一つに統一しろよな！
We don't really mesh here.
Let's at least have a coherent view of the world, you no-good geezer.
ﾀﾞﾒﾀﾞﾒｱﾙ！
(落)お前らの さっきの格好は➡
This isn't going to work, uh-huh.
Did the costumes you were wearing before mesh?
何が統一されてたんですか！
どこに ｾﾝｽがあったんですか！
Where was the logic in that?
いい加減にしてよ ﾎﾝﾄ もう！
Gimme a break.
In what universe is there a house that's haunted by Jason and a dead samurai?!
どこの世界に
落ち武者と ｼﾞｪｲｿﾝが➡
共演してる 肝試しがあるんだよ！
落さん！
Ochi-san. It wasn't Jason. I was Jackson.
ｼﾞｪｲｿﾝじゃない！ ｼﾞｬｸｿﾝです！
ｵﾚのｵﾘｼﾞﾅﾙだから｡
どうでもいいから！
He's an original character I created.
Who the hell cares?!
お前の ｺﾞﾐｸｽﾞみたいなﾌﾟﾗｲﾄﾞ
どうでもいいから！
I don't give a damn about your wretched creations!
Ochi-san!
(係員)落さん！
お客さん来ました！
We've got customers!!
お二人様 ご案内！
A party of two is on its way up.
えっ!? もう！
まだ 夕方だよ！
Already? But it's not even dark yet.
もういいや！
ぶっつけ本番だ！
Oh, whatever.
We'll just have to wing it!
You guys head over to the temple gardens.
とりあえず ｷﾐたちは寺の庭に！
That's where we'll set up the haunted house.
そこが 肝試しの会場だから…
あっ！
それは いらねえ！
どれだけ やる気満々なんだよ！
You won't need those!!
Do you guys really want to be a part of this or not?
Daddy, I'm scared.
(子)父ちゃん ﾎﾞｸ怖いよ…｡
(父)ｱﾊﾊﾊﾊ！ 大丈夫だ！
父ちゃんがついてるから！
Don't worry. Daddy's right here with you.
(子)だって 今にも
なんか出そう…｡
But it feels like something could jump out at any moment.
お前！
(皿がぶつかり合う音)
Hey you, stop making so much noise with those dishes.
さっきから
皿 ｶﾞﾁｬｶﾞﾁｬうるせぇよ！
I told you to leave them behind, didn't I?
だから 置いてこいって
言っただろうが！
(神楽)だって これ
こんなに いっぱいあるね！
Yeah, but look how many there are.
何これ？ 何に使うｱﾙ？
What is this? What are they used for?
It's just like in that Bancho Sarayashiki story, Kagura-chan.
[Note: A famous Japanese ghost story about a maid who is falsely accused of breaking a ceramic plate and subsequently dropped in a well.]
それ あれだよ 神楽ちゃん！
『番町皿屋敷』｡
１枚 ２枚って数えていって
９枚目で…➡
She counts all the dishes one by one and after the ninth one she says,
[Note: Her ghost comes out of the well every night counting dishes but is always short one dish.]
"There's one missing. I curse you!" and then pounces on you.
｢１枚足りない うらめしや～｣って
襲いかかるんだよ！
One...two...
１枚 ２枚… あれ？
本当に １枚たりないよ｡
Huh? You're right. There is one missing.
うん… あれ？ おい
あそこに落ちてんの…｡
Hm? Huh?
Hey, it's right over there.
(新八/神楽)あっ！
Ah!
(神楽)私 取りに行ってくるｱﾙ｡
落ち着けってぇの！
I'll go get it.
Just chill!
隠れてるの ﾊﾞﾚるだろ！
Or you'll spoil our hiding place.
I've already heard everything...
もう 全部 聞こえてんですけど…｡
(神楽)だって もともと
１枚足りないのに➡
But if we're short one dish to start out with and we're missing one,
もう１枚足りなかったら
２枚も足りないよ！
then that means we're actually short two.
神楽ちゃん
もういいじゃない！
Kagura-chan, don't worry about it.
Just say, "There's two missing. I curse you."
｢２枚足りない うらめしや～｣で
いいじゃない！
No, I don't want to. That's not how the story goes.
ｲﾔｱﾙ！ 設定が ｸﾞﾀﾞｸﾞﾀﾞね！
ﾀﾞﾒだって 神楽ちゃ～ん!!
うわあぁ～!!
No, don't! Kagura-chan!
(皿が割れる音)
お… お皿が…｡
Th...The dishes...
(父)お前は 優しい子だな｡
That was nice of you.
(子)だって とっても
かわいそうだったから…｡
Well, I felt sorry for her.
Mmm... I got candy!
あめ玉 もらっちゃったさ｡
What do you mean, "I got candy"?
あめ玉 もらっちゃったさ～｡
じゃねえよ！
なに哀れみうけてんのさ！
Why is a vengeful ghost receiving pity from people?!
(落)ちょっと ﾎﾝﾄ 頼むよ！
すごい ｸﾞﾀﾞｸﾞﾀﾞっぷりだったよ！
Come on! Pull yourselves together!
That was pathetic!
(落)ﾎﾞｸが 友人の結婚式でやった
出し物より ｸﾞﾀﾞｸﾞﾀﾞだったよ！
It was lamer than my karaoke performance at my friend's wedding.
だって これ 皿が ｶﾞﾁｬｶﾞﾁｬ
身動きとりずらいね！
Yeah, but it's hard to move around with all these dishes clattering about.
ﾌﾘｽﾋﾞｰか 何かに変更してよ！
Can't we change them to Frisbees or something?
(落)ﾌﾘｽﾋﾞｰが １枚 ２枚って
いった どんな恨みを持った幽霊!?
So you're gonna count one Frisbee, two...
What the hell kind of vengeful grudge are you gonna have?
これ以上 皿割ったら 町内会の
予算 食いつぶしちゃうよ｡
If you break any more dishes, you'll exhaust the community budget!
しかたない… どんな感じでやるか
次 ﾎﾞｸが 手本 見せるから➡
I have no choice!
I'll show you how it's done.
よく見ててよ！
わかりました！
Now, watch carefully.
Gotcha.
じゃあ ｵﾚたち その間
喫茶店にでも行って➡
While you do that, we'll go kill time at a coffee shop or something.
時間つぶしてま～す！
人の話 聞いてた!?
Are you even listening?
っていうか ﾀﾞﾒ～!! 帰らないで！
いいから 帰っちゃ ｲﾔ～!!
And, no! Don't leave!
Huh? Why are you putting so much effort into this?
Please don't leave!
ｱﾝﾀ なにそんなに
がんばっちゃってんの？
いや…｡
Well...
ｺｲﾂ 金が目当てｱﾙよ！
もしくは 女ｱﾙ｡
He's doing it for money.
Or maybe a woman.
うっ…｡
…で 落さん！
So, Ochi-san!
ﾎﾞｸら どうすればいいんですか？
あっ あぁ… そうだね…｡
What do you want us to do?
O...Oh, yeah.
ﾎﾞｸも だてに 毎年 この行事に
参加してるわけじゃないからね｡
I haven't been participating in this year after year for nothing, you know.
去年なんて 何人の女の子を
泣かしたことか｡
Like last year... I can't even remember how many girls I made cry in fear.
落さん！
次のお客さんが来ました！
Ochi-san, the next customer is here.
ｽﾀﾝﾊﾞｲ よろしく！
Please stand by.
So they've come... Our next victims...
来たようだね… 次の獲物が｡
You guys go hide over there.
ｷﾐたちは
あっちに隠れていたまえ！
Now watch me carefully and try to mimic my technique.
まぁ 技を盗むつもりで
しっかり 見ててよ！
それじゃ！
ちょっと行ってくるよ！
Okay then, I'm off.
(係員)へい らっしゃい！
あっ!?
Welcome.
Oh...
(おりょう)２名で お願いします！
Two, please.
落さん ﾔﾊﾞｲ…｡
Ochi-san...
You're in trouble now.
I told you, I hate these things.
(お妙)も～！ 私 こういうの
苦手だって 言ってるのに…｡
Oh come on, what's the harm of getting scared once in a while?
まぁまぁ たまには
こういうのも いいんじゃない！
(おりょう)ちょっと そんなに
くっつかないでよ お妙｡
Hey! Don't cling to me so tightly, Otae.
It's difficult to walk.
(おりょう)歩きにくいでしょ｡
(お妙)ﾎﾝﾄに 私 ﾀﾞﾒなの！
Seriously, I'm really bad with stuff like this.
(お妙)おりょう
置いていかないでね｡
Oryo, don't leave me.
ｱﾊﾊﾊﾊ！ またまた！
ｱﾝﾀに 怖いものなんてあるわけ…｡
There you go again.
You're not scared of anything...
ﾎﾝﾄ ﾀﾞﾒなの！ ﾏｼﾞだから
ﾏｼﾞで ﾏｼﾞだから！
I'm telling you, I can't take it!
I'm serious. Dead serious.
怖いの！ 怖すぎるの!!
I'm scared. I'm too scared!
You're way scarier...
ｱﾝﾀのほうが 怖いんだけど…｡
Don't leave my side, okay?
(お妙)離れないでね｡
離れないでね｡
Don't leave my side, okay?
ﾌｯﾌﾌﾌﾌﾌ！
(２人)ｷﾞｬｱｰ!!
ﾍｯﾍｯﾍｯﾍ！ ちょろいもんだよ｡
That was easy.
やめて！ ﾎﾝﾄ やめて！
私 ﾎﾝﾄに…➡
Stop it. Seriously, stop it.
Seriously...
怖えぇっつってんだろうがあぁ!!
I said I'm bad at this!!
ええっ!!
♪♪～
ｲﾔｯ！ もう ｲﾔｯ！
帰ろう ねぇ帰ろう！
No, I've had enough!
Let's go home, okay? Let's go!
ちょっと待って
落ち着いてよ お妙｡
Hold on a second.
Just calm down, Otae!
What's up with that girl?
《なんだ あの娘
どうなってるんだ？
What's going on?
ｸｿｯ！ かくなる上は…》
Damn, in that case... Phase Two.
(２人)うわっ！ ｷﾞｬｱｧｰ!!
HinTama!
[Note: HinTama is slang for Hitodama, the "spirits of the dead that are in the form of firefoxes". It is also a play on GinTama.]
(お妙)火ん玉～!!
火ん玉だわ！ 火ん玉だわ！
Hintama! They're Hintama!!
(お妙)ｷﾞｬｱｧ！
おいっ ちょっと！
死んじゃう 死んじゃうって！
Hey, stop! You're killing her!
She'll die!
何やってんの ｷﾐ ちょっと！
はしゃぐにしても限度が！
What're you doing?
Come on! Even freaking out has its limits...
ｷﾞｬ～ｯ！ 気持悪い！
Gross!
ぶぉぉっ！
よかったっすね｡ より
落ち武者っぽくなりましたよ！
Good job.
You really look like a fallen samurai now.
落ちすぎじゃねえのか？
地面にめり込んでるよ もう｡
You've fallen too far though...
You're almost half-buried into the ground.
(神楽)ﾊﾞﾝｼﾞｰね 裸族の
ﾊﾞﾝｼﾞｰｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ並みに危険な落ち方ね｡
Yeah, like a bungee jumping accident.
Your fall was as dangerous as bungee jumping naked.
もう ｲﾔだぁ！ 今年 もう最悪！
もう ｲﾔ！ ｽﾀｯﾌから客から➡
I've had it! This is the worst year ever!
I can't take it!
Both the staff and customers are just totally unreasonable!
ﾒﾁｬｸﾁｬなﾔﾂばっかり
じゃねえかよ もう！
おいおい お盆に そんな
ｾﾘﾌ吐くもんじゃないよ｡
Hey, come on. That's no way to talk during O-bon Festival.
[Note: O-bon is a Buddhist tradition of honoring the spirits of the dead.]
今年は まだ残ってるだろうが！
The year isn't over yet.
そういうｾﾘﾌは やることやって
大晦日に吐きましょうや｡
You can say that on New Year's Eve after you've done everything you can do.
(落)そんなこと言ったってさ
もう こんな ｸﾞﾀﾞｸﾞﾀﾞ感は➡
Sure, that's easy for you to say.
I bet everyone's heard how lame this is.
人々の耳に伝わってるよ｡
もう 客なんて来ないよ これ｡
No one's gonna come now.
ああ ﾀﾞﾒだ！
町内会の役員も降ろされる！
It's over. They'll kick me out of the neighborhood association now!
せっかく でかい顔して
ふんぞり返れる地位まで➡
And after all my struggles to reach a position where I could lord it over everyone!
のぼりつめたってのに！
ﾎﾞｸの居場所は
町内会にしかないってのに！
The neighborhood association was the only place left for me.
こんな肝試し
祭りの余興じゃねえか！
Isn't this haunted house just a sideshow in the festival anyway?
そんな ｽｷﾔｷの隅っこに
忘れられた 脂身みてえな➡
You sound pitiful, just like the piece of fat that's been forgotten in the corner of the sukiyaki pot.
寂しいこと言ってんじゃないよ！
(落)いや…
ｽｷﾔｷの脂身のほうが ﾏｼさ｡
No, the sukiyaki fat is better off than me.
ﾎﾞｸはね 家庭にも職場にも
居場所なんてないんだ…｡
I get no respect at home or even at work.
会社では 万年平社員 机は窓際｡
I'm scorned at the office as dead wood.
My desk is by the window.
[Note: In Japan, often useless, unneeded employees are seated by the window.]
ついた あだ名は 落ち武者｡
I was nicknamed "Ochimusha."
[Note: Ochimusha means defeated samurai.]
上司には叱られ…➡
Every day, my boss scolded me...
後輩には笑われる毎日｡
...and my subordinates laughed at me.
ﾘｽﾄﾗも決まって…➡
I was laid off.
妻とも もう別れたしね…｡
And my wife...
She left me...
でも そんな ﾎﾞｸでも輝ける
場所を見つけることができた！
But even someone like me was able to find a place where I can shine.
それが ここ！
And that was here.
ﾎﾞｸを見て
恐れおののき逃げる人々｡
People got scared and ran away when they saw me.
まるで 自分が
偉くなった気分だった…｡
It made me feel big and important.
みんなをもっと驚かそうと
いろんな仕掛けを考えて…｡
I even devised my own clever schemes to scare the customers.
だから ﾎﾞｸは 何としても
この肝試しを成功させたいんだよ｡
That's why...I have to make this haunted house a success, no matter what!
ｷﾐたちには わかって
もらえないだろうけどさ…｡
I don't expect you to understand how I feel...
それに こんなこと 恥ずかしくて
話したくなかったんだけどね…｡
Besides, I didn't really want to tell you since it's so embarrassing...
落さん…｡
Ochi-san...
恥ずかしい？ いいんじゃねえの｡
Embarrassing? Who cares?
ﾃﾒｴで生きると決めた
場所なんだろ？
This is the place you decided to live, right?
恥ずかしがってどうするよ｡
What's being embarrassed going to do?
何かを本気で やりとげてえなら
四の五の言わず 魂でぶつかれよ｡
If you're really serious about accomplishing something,
then stop grumbling and throw your heart and soul into it.
その魂が本物なら
誰にだって伝わるだろうよ｡
If you give it your all, then everyone will be able to feel it.
それが 肝試しだろうが
なんだろうが…｡
Whether it be this haunted house or anything else...
お膳立ては任せとけ｡
盛り上げるだけ盛り上げたら➡
Leave the setup to us.
We'll reel them in and set 'em up for you to close in for the kill.
最後は ｱﾝﾀが決めりゃいいさ｡
坂田さん…！
Sakata-san...
ﾎﾞｸ 魂でぶつかります！
よ～し やるぞ！
I'll make this event a success if it kills me!
Let's do this!
銀さん…｡
Gin-san...
ああでも言わないと
どこまでも落ちていくだろ｡
If I didn't say that to him, there's no telling how far he would have fallen.
落だからね 名前が落だからね｡
Well, his name, "Ochi" does mean, "to fall."
(ﾍﾄﾞﾛ)すみません
１人なんですけど いいですか？
Excuse me. I'm by myself, but may I go in?
(ﾍﾄﾞﾛ)いやぁ ﾄﾞｷﾄﾞｷするな！
Oh gosh, I'm so nervous.
ﾎﾞｸ 怖がりのくせに つい
こういう所 来ちゃうんですよ｡
I'm such a scaredy-cat, but I can't resist stuff like this.
ﾊﾞｶでしょ？
Pretty silly of me, huh?
(係員)いえいえいえ！
滅相もございません！
Oh no, no, no. Not at all!
あれ？ なんで泣いてるんですか？
Oh? Why are you crying?
ひぃぃ… お一人様 ご案内！
Yeow... One customer on his way!
やばい… 落さん やばい｡
Crap... Ochi-san's in trouble...
落だからね 名前が落だからね｡
He's about to live up to his name.
You just wait and see...
(落)見てろ… 次は
必ず ﾊﾞｼｯと決めるぞ！
I'll make this next one perfect.
意地を見せてやる！
I'll show you what I'm made of!
(落)あっ… 来た！
Oh, here he comes.
♪♪～
えぇぇっ！
(落)何 あれ!? なんで
化け物が肝試ししてんの!?
What the hell is that?
What's a monster doing at a haunted house?
ﾎﾞｸより はるかに怖いじゃん！
肝試す必要ないじゃん！
He's so much scarier than me.
There's no need for him to even be here!
やばい 逃げ…｡
おっと 逃げちゃ ﾀﾞﾒだぜ！
Damnit... I'm outta here!
Hang on there. You can't run away.
魂で ぶつかるんじゃ
なかったのかよ？
Weren't you going to throw your heart and soul into this?
しかし ｷﾐね
あれ ちょっと怖すぎ｡
Yeah but, he's way too scary.
≪(神楽)お皿が１枚…➡
One dish...
お皿が２枚 お皿３枚 以下省略｡
Two dishes, three dishes, a bunch of dishes.
(神楽)あれ １枚足りない…｡
What's this? There's one missing.
うらめしや…｡
A curse upon you!
《危ない！ お嬢ちゃん
危ないって 食べられちゃうよ》
Watch out!
Little girl, be careful. He's gonna eat you!
や～っ！
ひぃっ！
(落)あれ…？
Huh?
わ～っ！
Does that monster...look scared?
(落)化け物が…
なんか あれ ﾋﾞﾋﾞってない？
ﾌﾘｽﾋﾞｰが１枚 ﾌﾘｽﾋﾞｰが２枚…
以下省略｡ あれ １枚足りない｡
One Frisbee, two Frisbees, a bunch of Frisbees.
What's this? There's one missing.
うらめしﾜﾝ！
"I curse you...woof!"
(落)なんか勝手に設定作ってる！
He's just making stuff up as he goes!!
ﾆﾝﾆｸが１個 ﾆﾝﾆｸが２個 以下省略｡
One garlic, two garlic, a bunch of garlic...
(落)ﾆﾝﾆｸ!? 間違ってるよ！
それ弱点だよ 弱点数えてるよ！
Garlic?! That's wrong!
That's your weakness!
You're counting your weak point!
あれ １個足りない…｡
What's this? There's one missing...
うらめしﾄﾞﾗ！
(落)語呂わりぃよ！
"I dracu-curse you!!"
That doesn't even go together!
(ﾍﾄﾞﾛ)ひぃ～!!
And one to rule them all... "Fallen samurai," here, a snack.
落ち武者 ﾊｲ ｽｰﾅｯｸ｡
(新八たち)ｽｰﾅｯｸ｡
Snack, snack.
Snack? What? What are they talking about?
《ｽﾅｯｸ？ 何？ 何言ってんの？》
Snack, snack.
あっ… 何これ!?
What's this?!
《落:ﾎﾟｹｯﾄにｽﾅｯｸが ごっそり…》
My pockets are full of snacks...
Snack, snack.
Don't tell me they want me to count them...
まさか 数えろと!?
(銀時たち)ｽｰﾅｯｸ｡
So they want me to count these snacks that have absolutely nothing to do with me?
《縁もゆかりもない
このｽﾅｯｸを数えろと!?》
Snack, snack...
(銀時たち)ｽｰﾅｯｸ ｽｰﾅｯｸ｡
《落:よし… ﾎﾞｸだって
やってみせる！》
All right. I'll do it.
One snack.
ｽﾅｯｸが１個… ｽﾅｯｸが２個…｡
Two snacks.
以下省略｡
あれ？ １個足りない…｡
A bunch of snacks.
What's this? There's one missing...
うらめしやでござるぅ～!!
[Note: "-degozaru" is a stereotypical samurai way of ending one's sentences.]
"I curse you -degozaru!!"
えいっ！
ひやぁ～!!
Well, I really enjoyed that demonstration.
いやぁ
おもしろいﾃﾞﾓﾝｽﾄﾚｰｼｮﾝでした｡
新しいﾀｲﾌﾟの肝試しでしたね｡
It certainly was a great haunted house game, wasn't it? But...
でも… 殺生は いけない｡
It's wrong to take a life.
You almost stepped on this bug.
あやうく虫を踏むところでしたよ｡
落だからね… 名前が落だからね｡
Well, "Ochi" does mean "To Fall." Yes, it does.
(落)だぁ…｡
落さん…｡
Ochi-san...
(係員)いらっしゃいませ｡
(神楽)あっ お客さんｱﾙよ｡
Welcome.
Oh, another customer.
(落)もういいよ…｡
Never mind already.
I've finally lost the only sanctuary I had.
ﾎﾞｸは とうとう唯一の居場所も
失ってしまった…｡
I'll leave the rest up to you.
あとは ｷﾐたちに任せるよ｡
それで どうするんですか？
あきらめちゃうんですか？
So what are you going to do now?
Are you just going to give up?
There's nothing to give up on.
あきらめるも なにも➡
This is the kind of life I was meant to live after all.
しょせん ﾎﾞｸには
こんな生き方が お似合いなのさ｡
待ちな！
Hang on!!
また逃げるのか？ ｱﾝﾀ いっつも
逃げてばかりじゃねえか！
You're running away again?
All you do is run away.
ｱﾝﾀ さっき肝試しが➡
You just said the haunted house was the only place you had.
唯一の居場所だって
言ってたけどよ➡
But that's wrong.
それは 間違いだな｡
え… えっ？
What...?
今まで戦ってこないで逃げ続け➡
You always ran away without a fight and that's how you ended up here.
たどり着いた場所が
ここだっただけだ｡
ここらで 本物の肝試しを
してみちゃどうだい？
How's about taking a real stab at life, now?
A real stab at life?
本物の肝試し？
今度は ｱﾝﾀが肝を試す番なんだよ｡
Yeah, it's time for you to test your courage.
落さん… 男は 毎日➡
Ochi-san... For a man, every day is like a haunted house.
肝試しを
生きてるようなもんなんだ｡
それをしてねえと
いつしか腐っちまう｡
If we never tested our courage, we'd just rot away.
魂が死んじまうんだよ！
Our heart and soul would just die.
自分の居場所を
本当に守りてぇなら➡
If you really want to protect the place you call your own, then
その魂
思いっきり ぶつけてみな！
...throw that heart and soul into it with all your might.
Come on, hurry. The customer will be here any minute now.
さぁ 早く！
お客さんが来ちゃいますよ｡
(落)はい！
Okay.
Here she comes...
(落)来た！
♪♪～
A loser like me...
《落:こんな
どうしようもない ﾎﾞｸが…》
《落:あれだけ
逃げ続けてきた ﾎﾞｸが…｡
The one who kept running away from everything...
やっぱり ここは… でも！》
I can't do this after all...
But...
♪♪～
I don't ever want to feel that way again!
あんな思いは もうたくさんだ！
《落ち武者だった
昨日までの自分に…｡
To the "Ochimusha" I was yesterday...
さよならだ！》
I'm saying goodbye!!
うらめしやでござ…｡
(お軽)ん？
"I curse y..."
O...Oka...
お… おか…｡
るぅ～!!
ｲﾃﾃﾃ…｡
(衝撃音)
Ow...Ouch...
お… おか… お軽｡
Oka...Okaru...
お… お軽…｡
O...Okaru.
C-Come ba-ba-ba-back to me!
ｵ… ｵﾚのとこに
もど… もど もど 戻って…｡
ｱﾀｯ！ 舌噛んじゃった!?
Ouch, I bit my tongue...
ﾌﾟｯ！ ｱﾊﾊﾊﾊｯ！
ｱﾝﾀって いつも
かっこつかないんだから…｡
You always bungle things...
いや その…｡
Um...well...
You're such a fool.
ﾊﾞｶね そのために
ここまで来たんじゃない｡
That's why I came here.
えっ!? お… お軽 お前…｡
Huh...
O-Okaru... You...
何も言わないでいいから…｡
Don't say anything.
Just let me come home with you.
ｱﾝﾀんとこに帰らせて｡
♪♪～
結局 落さんが勝手に１人で➡
So it looks like Ochi-san was the one who brought up the separation,
別れ話を
持ち出しただけだったんですね｡
but his wife never agreed to it.
Yeah, both of them were scared to be honest with each other.
２人とも素直になるのが
怖かっただけｱﾙ｡
Yeah, it looks that way.
まぁ そういうことかな｡
Good for them.
(神楽)いいなぁ… 銀ちゃん
私も お祭り行きたいｱﾙ｡
Gin-chan, I want to go to the festival too.
何言ってんだ｡ ｵﾚたちは
肝試しっつう仕事が残ってんだろ｡
What are you talking about?
We still have this haunted house job to finish.
What? We still have to do that?
あれ？ まだやるの？
Oh, now that I think about it, Ochi-san didn't scare anyone.
あっ そういえば
落さん 結局 誰も怖がらせてねえ｡
まっ いっか！
Whatever!
We're trying to make this sound like a good story at the end,
いや… なんか普通に いい話で
まとめようとしてるんですけど…｡
ｵﾁとか ないんですけど…！
[Note: "Punch line" is "Ochi" in Japanese.]
but don't you have a punch line or something to end with?
No, this is the punch line: because his name is Ochi.
(神楽)いや 落だから｡
名前が 落だからね｡
[A woman...]
[Comes...]
[Holding a garbage bag...]
[And then...]
[She watched.]
[An Unusual Episode of GinTama.]
[Note: "Yo ni mo kimyo na GinTama" a parody of the popular mystery show "Yo ni mo kimyo na monogatari" -Tales of the Unusual.]
[Always...]
[Help by Separating Your Trash.]
[Gintoki makes the mistake of throwing away his JUMP on non-combustible trash day.]
[While there, Gintoki sees... Starting next episode, the Fuyo Story!!]